<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Deliberate Practice | Bro Kaizen]]></title>
  <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/categories/deliberate-practice/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-16T01:05:57-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://bro-kaizen.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[bro_kaizen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Husband Your Gumption]]></title>
    <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/17/husband-your-gumption/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-17T01:05:07-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/17/husband-your-gumption</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[Beware this caveat pertaining to [gumption and character](http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/16/on-gumption-and-character/)!

<!--more-->

Gumption can be temporarily depleted, which will slow your roll on deliberate practice and many other good parts of your life. 

Deliberate Practice has 3 inputs:

1. Time
2. Knowledge
3. Gumption

Ingredient #1, time management, has been abundantly covered by [far](http://terrytao.wordpress.com/2008/08/07/on-time-management/) [greater](http://www.entrepreneur.com/article/220418) [powers](http://blog.penelopetrunk.com/2009/01/08/5-time-management-tricks-i-learned-from-years-of-hating-tim-ferriss/) than Bro Kaizen. Ingredient #2 has been treated elsewhere, [on](http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/12/growth-mentality/) and [off](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carol_Dweck) this blog. Let&#8217;s focus on ingredient #3, &#8220;Gumption.&#8221;

If you expend your gumption fruitlessly, by hours spent copy-and-pasting long columns of figures between Excel spreadsheets, or memorizing vast quantities of facts by rote, you will lack the wherewithal to tackle the design-a-rocket-thruster project when it is offered to you. Similarly, in your drained state, you&#8217;ll lack the discipline to stick to your diet, wake up early to visit the gym, man up and go talk to that pretty girl, and avoid the time-wasting temptation of Reddit/Television. Resistance to each of these negative life ingredients draws from the same reservoir.

Therefore you must husband your gumption reserves, protect them from depletion on stupid things, and instead expend them solely on deliberate practice and worthwhile tasks (aka rocket engine design). Perhaps the most practical way to accomplish this gumption husbandry is to construct a &#8220;life system&#8221; wherein positive processes and outcomes happen by default. For example,

* Design a trip to the gym into your day (perhaps by joining one between your house and job, such that you pass it every day anyway and you might as well go in). 
* Put a pullup bar in your bathroom door so you end up doing a few reps on your way to the shower. (Idea stolen from [Matt Might](http://matt.might.net/articles/hacking-strength/))
* Pay your housemate to withold your wallet and phone every day after work until you complete your 1 hour of Pashto language practice.

We want the _system_ to do the heavy motivational lifting/tiresome shlepping automatically, thereby freeing your gumption reservoir for the vital tasks for which it is on the critical path or is the limiting reactant. ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Deliberate Practice in Action]]></title>
    <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/15/a-pithy-example-of-deliberate-practice/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-15T00:46:52-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/15/a-pithy-example-of-deliberate-practice</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[Wiser and more experienced writers than Bro Kaizen are considering Deliberate Practice, about which topic we began [harping](http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/14/deliberate-practice/) earlier this week. Here's perhaps the pithiest example of DP yet---this is the whole thing in a nutshell.

<!--more-->

<blockquote><p>Consider the activity of two basketball players practicing free throws for one hour. Player A shoots 200 practice shots, Player B shoots 50. The Player B retrieves his own shots, dribbles leisurely and takes several breaks to talk to friends. Player A has a colleague who retrieves the ball after each attempt. The colleague keeps a record of shots made. If the shot is missed the colleague records whether the miss was short, long, left or right and the shooter reviews the results after every 10 minutes of practice. To characterize their hour of practice as equal would hardly be accurate. Assuming this is typical of their practice routine and they are equally skilled at the start, which would you predict would be the better shooter after only 100 hours of practice?</p><footer><strong>&#8212;Aubrey Daniels</strong></footer></blockquote>

The quote is brazenly stolen from [here](http://aubreydaniels.com/pmezine/expert-performance-apologies-dr-ericsson-it-not-10000-hours-deliberate-practice). Written glibly like this, Aubrey and I are making it sound easy, when in fact the essence of the thing is just precisely the opposite. Of course Deliberate Practice is not easy&#8212;_that&#8217;s the point._ It&#8217;s hard. And it is for that reason that you must [nurture](http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/17/husband-your-gumption/) your supply of [gumption](http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/16/on-gumption-and-character/) in order to tackle it. ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Deliberate Practice]]></title>
    <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/14/deliberate-practice/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-14T22:11:59-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/14/deliberate-practice</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[If you're overweight, you don't earn physical fitness by spending three days doing a cardio circuit with your roomate, two days following a diet that your girlfriend invented, four days with Mark Rippetoe's [Starting Strength](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_Rippetoe), and then going to sit on the couch. A piecemeal (and half-heartedly implemented) approach like that is **destined to fail.**

But fear not---there is a better way:

<!--more-->

The better approach is called &#8220;deliberate practice,&#8221; a term that I have shamelessly stolen from [Geoff Colvin](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geoffrey_Colvin), [James Clear](http://jamesclear.com/deliberate-practice), and [others](http://www.artofmanliness.com/2010/11/07/the-secret-of-great-men-deliberate-practice/). 

## I. An Implementation of the Growth Mentality&#8217;s Objectives

Deliberate practice is the best-known method for _executing_ or _implementing_ the objectives decided by your growth mentality. In fact, participating in deliberate practice is such a strong predictor of success in a variety of athletic and intellectual fields (even chess!) that it has been called an &#8220;unfair advantage.&#8221; Needless to say, at this blog, we try to deploy the maximum possible quantity of unfair advantages in your favor. 

Let&#8217;s construct a short working definition of deliberate practice by examining its attributes:


* DP is goal driven, ie. is working towards some objective (bowling 70 km per hour in cricket consistently/learning 100 Pashto words per week/whatever)
* DP involves breaking complex tasks down into tiny, mechanical chunks that [require no talent](/things-that-take-no-talent) ie. 1) Sit in your chair in a silent room, 2) load Rosetta Stone software, 3) Repeat Pashto phrases back to the computer for 1 hour, etc. Each of those could easily be done by a very stupid person, who would balk utterly if I commanded him to &#8220;Learn Pashto!&#8221;
* DP is repeatable, ie. you can come back tomorrow and learn more Pashto vocabulary using the same (sit >> load software >> repeat words) algorithm as you used today
* DP involves a tight iterative feedback loop, where good or bad outcomes are connected to your actions in near real time. For example, the Rosetta Stone software will grade your pronunciation as soon as you finish talking.
* DP is difficult

## II. The Imposition of Regularity on Seemingly Dissimilar Problem Domains

In a way, DP is a method for standardizing disparate problem domains. Rather than discovering a new meta-method for improvements in each sphere of your life, you can try to make the problem fit a DP shaped mold. So once you&#8217;ve gained proficiency in deliberate practice, you&#8217;ll start to abstract away the complexity in learning widely different skills. Learning good bowling form in cricket will start to seem rather like the process of figuring out node.js, which in turn will seem similar to developing a humorous personality. 


## III. The Fault Tolerant Temperament
<span class='pullquote-right' data-pullquote='&#8220;If we knew what the hell we were doing, it wouldn&#8217;t be called research, would it?&#8221;'>
Of course, deliberate practice likely won&#8217;t work perfectly the first time you try it, and in fact you might discover, midway through learning a given skill, that it will never work at all. And that&#8217;s fine&#8212;perhaps you need expert instruction, a reliable reference text, or some other boost. Albert Einstein famously quipped, &#8220;If we knew what the hell we were doing, it wouldn&#8217;t be called research, would it?&#8221; The point is that a methodical approach is certainly better than flailing about a-systematically. After you approach a few disparate problems like this, you will start to develop a very handy sort of DP-intuition that will serve in very good stead for years to come.
</span>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
