<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Gumption | Bro Kaizen]]></title>
  <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/categories/gumption/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-16T01:05:57-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://bro-kaizen.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[bro_kaizen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Husband Your Gumption]]></title>
    <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/17/husband-your-gumption/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-17T01:05:07-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/17/husband-your-gumption</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[Beware this caveat pertaining to [gumption and character](http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/16/on-gumption-and-character/)!

<!--more-->

Gumption can be temporarily depleted, which will slow your roll on deliberate practice and many other good parts of your life. 

Deliberate Practice has 3 inputs:

1. Time
2. Knowledge
3. Gumption

Ingredient #1, time management, has been abundantly covered by [far](http://terrytao.wordpress.com/2008/08/07/on-time-management/) [greater](http://www.entrepreneur.com/article/220418) [powers](http://blog.penelopetrunk.com/2009/01/08/5-time-management-tricks-i-learned-from-years-of-hating-tim-ferriss/) than Bro Kaizen. Ingredient #2 has been treated elsewhere, [on](http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/12/growth-mentality/) and [off](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carol_Dweck) this blog. Let&#8217;s focus on ingredient #3, &#8220;Gumption.&#8221;

If you expend your gumption fruitlessly, by hours spent copy-and-pasting long columns of figures between Excel spreadsheets, or memorizing vast quantities of facts by rote, you will lack the wherewithal to tackle the design-a-rocket-thruster project when it is offered to you. Similarly, in your drained state, you&#8217;ll lack the discipline to stick to your diet, wake up early to visit the gym, man up and go talk to that pretty girl, and avoid the time-wasting temptation of Reddit/Television. Resistance to each of these negative life ingredients draws from the same reservoir.

Therefore you must husband your gumption reserves, protect them from depletion on stupid things, and instead expend them solely on deliberate practice and worthwhile tasks (aka rocket engine design). Perhaps the most practical way to accomplish this gumption husbandry is to construct a &#8220;life system&#8221; wherein positive processes and outcomes happen by default. For example,

* Design a trip to the gym into your day (perhaps by joining one between your house and job, such that you pass it every day anyway and you might as well go in). 
* Put a pullup bar in your bathroom door so you end up doing a few reps on your way to the shower. (Idea stolen from [Matt Might](http://matt.might.net/articles/hacking-strength/))
* Pay your housemate to withold your wallet and phone every day after work until you complete your 1 hour of Pashto language practice.

We want the _system_ to do the heavy motivational lifting/tiresome shlepping automatically, thereby freeing your gumption reservoir for the vital tasks for which it is on the critical path or is the limiting reactant. ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On Gumption and Character]]></title>
    <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/16/on-gumption-and-character/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-16T02:01:53-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/16/on-gumption-and-character</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[Gumption is the gasoline of man's life. It is the get-up-and-go, the stick-to-it-iveness, and the knocked-down-twice, stand-up-thrice fire inside you. If you run out of it, things will head south very quickly. You must cultivate this gumption, nurture it, and encourage it to grow. Every man possesses by nature a certain rate of gumption replenishment, which rate may be modified by nurture. As you nurture your rate of gumption replenishment, you will also tend to develop in parallel the ability to store more of it. I know of at least two ways to develop gumption:

<!--more-->


* Acclimatizing oneself to doing things that are hard (I am blatantly stealing this from [Mark Rippetoe](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_Rippetoe)&#8217;s book Starting Strength, in the chapter on deadlifts)
* Experiencing deprivation or scarcity

## I. Population Distribution of Gumption
There exists a gumption spectrum, upon which we can plot the positions of any given person. For rhetorical purposes, let&#8217;s bookend the spectrum with Navy SEALS (the ultra-elite amphibious stormtroopers of the American war machine) on one end, and the decadent, privileged children of the American upper-middle class on the other. (Oddly enough, the real aristocrats have often gone to great lengths to develop their children&#8217;s character, even in the most decadent of societies. For this reason there exist scathingly difficult elite boarding schools, summers spent as ranch hands, and dangerous or physics-based hobbies such as Polo and sailboat racing. Witness [Teddy Roosevelt](http://www.thecrimson.com/article/1957/12/12/theodore-roosevelt-at-harvard-pthe-crimson/), a blue blood through and through, and of a character to go toe-to-toe with the best of them. So the social class with the weakest character ends up being the upper-middle.)

Privileged Western white girls/JAP girls are usually typical examples of the no-gumption population, because they have been coddled their whole lives. Their parents have paid for their expensive apartments, unlimited mobile phone plans, vehicles/fuel/insurance, unbelievable quantities of international travel, etc. And if they are _hot_ privileged girls, clueless men have been buying them things/fawning over them/treating them like princesses for many years in a (guaranteed fruitless) attempt to get in their pants. They have experienced neither deprivation nor training in doing hard things, and these missing experiences have eroded/inhibited their character to an alarming degree. (To avoid accusations of hasty generalization, it is worth noting that this is certainly not an accurate description of _all_ privileged Western girls, merely some/many).

## II. Metrology

Obviously there is no such thing as a gumption meter, and it is difficult to measure directly. However, acceptable proxy metrics are available. Resistance to [decision fatigue](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Decision_fatigue) is a reliable predictor of gumption. If you hang out with some rich girls from your school for an afternoon, you&#8217;ll quickly realize that some of them can make a median of 2 decisions before becoming pissy and whiny&#8212;even trivial choices about which shoes to wear or restaurant/bar to visit wear them out. Conversely, imagine an afternoon spent with a Navy SEAL. He has spent his adult life making literal life-or-death decisions about which grade of armor piercing munitions to load in his helicopter, what rate to expel air from his lungs while submerged in icy saltwater, etc. You could require him to choose restaurants and find his way around a strange city for literally weeks on end (tasks which would incite many tantrums from someone on the other end of the spectrum), and he would not show the slightest sign of feeling pressured. 

## III. On Weak Men

Naturally, women are not to be found alone on the no-gumption end of the spectrum&#8212;there are plenty of weak, insipid men cowering there too, particularly in locales that have insulated the citizenry from deprivation, real work, and difficult tasks. And of course there are women on the SEAL end of the spectrum, as well. The Israelis have done a very impressive job of developing a gender-integrated military, complete with female commandos who demonstrate gumption with the best of them (undoubtedly far more gumption than I will ever possess). 

So the point is that gumption is another skill-based-upon-an-aptitude. Each of us is born with a natural level of gumption, but that level can be modified by intentional or unintentional nurture. Your job, as a man, even one in a &#8220;soft&#8221; society, is to take concious steps to regenerate and store more gumption.
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
