<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: College Advice | Bro Kaizen]]></title>
  <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/categories/college-advice/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-16T01:05:57-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://bro-kaizen.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[bro_kaizen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Dapper Propagandist]]></title>
    <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/12/27/apparel-and-propaganda/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-27T15:36:07-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/12/27/apparel-and-propaganda</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[The human animal is by and large easily bamboozled by the surface impressions of things. You will meet comparatively few people who see beyond the most superficial of apperances. Another way of stating this is that people want to be communicated with in a visual, quick, low-friction way. Communication is receiver based, so why not send them information on the channel that they listen to?

<!--more-->

## I. Frustration and the Technical Disposition

<span class='pullquote-right' data-pullquote='&#8220;Why can&#8217;t these stupid people see past shallow surface appearances and perceive the real essence of the thing!?&#8221;'>
For the technically inclined&#8212;those who peer at nearly-identical resistors whose ratings differ by a hundred thousand ohms, or pass days in contemplation of apparently-dissimilar manifolds that are nonetheless provably topologically equivalent&#8212;this is profoundly annoying. &#8220;Why can&#8217;t these stupid people see past shallow surface appearances and perceive the real essence of the thing!?&#8221; This objection can take many other forms, including but not limited to &#8220;Why doesn&#8217;t that girl notice how cool I am?&#8221; and &#8220;Why doesn&#8217;t my boss promote me?&#8221; Most of these objections are valid on their own merits, but in practice, attempts to compete with the nature of the human animal and the nurture of superficial, visual, TV-friendly modern culture is a fool&#8217;s game. A better strategy is to accept your fellow man for who he is, and use his foibles to your own advantage. This is doubly true when ordinary people are evaluating _you_ via their shallow heuristics.
</span>

## II. Clothing is a Propaganda Expense

<span class='caption-wrapper left'><img class='caption' src='/images/suit_guy.jpg' width='300' height='150' title='Fig. 1: Policemen believe them. [^1]'><span class='caption-text'>Fig. 1: Policemen believe them. [^1]</span></span>

As a male, you&#8217;re very likely not wholly enthused about shopping for clothes and worrying about how you look. Worrying about your haircut and spending time researching personal-appearance best practices probably seem like time wasted. If you file these time and money costs in the &#8220;Fun&#8221; or &#8220;Relaxing&#8221; categories, you&#8217;re right&#8212;they&#8217;re stupid, boring, and way less interesting than trucks, guns, dogs, weight lifting, and volunteering to help the needy. But that&#8217;s a categorization error, because spending money on your personal appearance is fundamentally a _propaganda_ cost, not something that you do for yourself. 

In other words, you spend gumption on clothes, hair, and other superficials not because those expenditures make you a more complete human or a better mathematician or plumber or whatever you are, but rather because other people are stupid and you can trivially control their minds by putting on a pair of trousers that they associate with some social role. You would be grossly remiss to pass up such an easy opportunity for mind control. And when you view it this way, clothes, hair, and social skills are a great bargain for you, the buyer&#8212;in general, changing people&#8217;s minds or behavior is very difficult and expensive (for reference, examine the costs associated with TV advertising), but you&#8217;ve got the chance to do it for the price of a clean shirt, sharp shoes, and a fresh haircut. 

<span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/punks.jpg' width='300' height='150' title='Fig. 2: London's burning. [^2]'><span class='caption-text'>Fig. 2: London&#8217;s burning. [^2]</span></span> 
 
  
## III. Country Tweeds and City Silks
But context is quite important. As a thought experiment, consider the two pairs of gentlemen shown in Figs. 1 and 2. The former shows a pair of blandly but respectably dressed fellows; the latter a pair of genuine 1980&#8217;s London punks. If the four men had an argument in Trafalgar Square, perhaps concerned with the relative merits of the Sex Pistols&#8217; and Roxy Music&#8217;s artistic ouvres, and this argument came to blows, whose story would the police believe, who would be handled more roughly, and who hauled unceremoniously to the paddy wagon? But if we consider that same altercation in a new venue, perhaps at a punk rock concert in Shoreditch where a rougher sort of street justice prevails, the ties and blazers would become an immediate liability.
 
Similarly, which of those men can a nice girl from Wimbleton use to gain social status amongst her friends? What if she&#8217;s a nice Ukrainian au pair? What if she&#8217;s a hipster chick in Brooklyn? Which fellow would be promoted first at work? To whom will the investors give money for a new startup? 

Obviously these men are a contrived example, selected for maximum contrast, but the principle holds in many less extreme cases. The point is that there&#8217;s not a single correct uniform for every situation. Tune your propaganda to the audience at hand. When in doubt, dress to impress the dominant power group in the vicinity.

## IV. Response as a Function of Power

Oddly enough, appearance-propaganda&#8217;s success rate will probably improve as you use it on people of higher social stature and power. This is because influential people tend to be busy, and therefore tend to rely on progressively quicker and easier heuristics as they rise through the world. As another thought experiment, consider trying to bamboozle a nine-year old into liking you with mere superficialities. Such a small child has all the time in the world to evaluate you slowly, and hasn&#8217;t yet been thoroughly socialized with his society&#8217;s coded system of appearances. You could of course make a favorable impression, but it might require quite a bit of time and effort spent on talking about toys and playing football&#8212;and even then, children often have a reliable nose for character and intentions, so the real substance of your personality would be relevant. Conversely, judges, policemen, CEO&#8217;s, and other similarly weighty folk are almost trivially biased in your favor by the briefest of efforts&#8212;perhaps something along the lines of shaving, standing up straight, and putting on a tie. This effect is partially responsible for the large number of gits in high places, who learned this technique long ago and have been using it to rise through hierarchies ever since.


## V. Actionable Advice
Surely some readers are wondering how to begin, having been dressed since time immemorial by girlfriends, mothers, or Adidas. There are many right answers here, and even more wrong ones. But a known-good starting point is to saunter into Charles Tyrwhitt, T.M. Lewin, Bonobos, Banana Republic, or J. Crew, and buy navy and brown trousers, light blue shirts with button-down collars, unobtrusively patterned socks, and a set of brown leather-soled wingtip brogues. Wear the shirts untucked with sleeves rolled up. Get some V-neck (never crew-neck!) undershirts, such that the white undershirt doesn&#8217;t show beneath your open collar. Furthermore, the shirts will be too wide, so you&#8217;ll need to take them to a tailor to be darted. This costs twelve pounds per shirt, so don&#8217;t be intimidated. Wearing your new duds, wander into a barbershop in the central business district of your city and tell them you need a haircut that works in the office and also in a bar. Congratulations&#8212;you are now better dressed than 90% of men, and this uniform will get you through 90% of situations in the modern middle-class life. Of course, much has been written on this topic, and it wouldn&#8217;t hurt to peruse [some](http://www.styleforum.net) [of](http://www.askandyaboutclothes.com/forum/) [the](http://putthison.com) [relevant](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alan_Flusser) [literature](http://properashell.com). 

Brotip: at work, a tried-and-true algorithm is to observe the fast-tracked managers/successful employees who are one or two levels above you in the social status/corporate rank hierarchy, and then gradually dress exactly like them.

[^1]: Image courtesy of [Paul Walker](https://www.flickr.com/photos/30591976@N05/)

[^2]: Image courtesy of [Tymtoi](https://www.flickr.com/photos/tymtoi/)]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On the Teleology of Womanizing]]></title>
    <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/12/15/on-competence-in-womanizing/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-15T00:22:59-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/12/15/on-competence-in-womanizing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[There are many reasons to become a competent womanizer, not least among which is the fact that you are biologically programmed for sex and therefore that the pursuit of women is inherently interesting. But philandering nirvana also brings some handy side benefits, of which more below.

<!--more-->

## I. To Redirect One&#8217;s Energies
Chief among these secondary benefits is that quickly handling the girl-chasing part of your life frees up time and effort for other tasks. The part of your brain that was formerly focussed on the pursuit of comely maidens will be liberated, and you can then redirect your energies toward worthy masculine pursuits such as reading Homer, becoming a proficient marksman with long- and short-barreled firearms, and learning how to train neural nets for fun and profit.

## II. A Pleasant Thought Experiment
Imagine this&#8212;if you already had a dozen smoking hot Victoria&#8217;s Secret models, of every conceivable sort and in various simultaneous combinations, available for immediate sex via a single Whatsapp message, you would likely run your life somewhat differently than you do now. 

You would probably become less interested in pursuing women for the sake of validating your ego, and more interested in other parts of your life. There would be fewer late nights in loud bars and less money spent on drinks. You might spend more time reading, improving your physical fitness, or developing meaningful relationships with people whose central activity is not gossipy text messaging and the pursuit of attention. 

## III. To Each His Own
Naturally, a single good woman could in principle satisfy your needs for female companionship and thereby confer the same second-order benefits as a reliable stable of girls. The method by which you &#8220;handle the girl-chasing part of your life&#8221; is only very loosely coupled to the reaping of these secondary benefits. But beware&#8212;for most young men in the Anglo-American world,[^1] a life committed to any but the very best of women is suboptimal in the best case and at worst hellishly emasculating. A good woman is very hard to find, so great caution is in order when awarding commitment.

## IV. Caveat Venator
Of course, the dozen-models example above is an extreme case. Only a tiny minority of men on earth enjoy that sort of privilege&#8212;and most of these are well connected fashion and entertainment industry types, who hold the keys to the industrial-scale attention/social status machinery that females crave so desperately. [Terry Richardson](http://www.highsnobiety.com/2010/01/28/pirelli-calendar-2010-a-full-look-nsfw/#slide-13) (link NSFW) springs to mind. Without inserting yourself in the process by which pretty young women are fêted before the broadest of publics, living like that is a low-probability outcome. But take heart&#8212;a stable of between five and ten reliable uncommitted girls (perhaps with temperatures in the 6-9 range) is eminently attainable for any competent man in a major city. Much has been written about how to attain this, often on finer, fatter publications than Bro Kaizen. 

## V. Common Misunderstandings
By no means is Bro Kaizen suggesting that interactions with females are not inherently interesting and valuable. You should at all times act in accordance with your nature, and therefore remain interested in sex with women for all the obvious reasons. Nor should you abandon your pursuit of the fair sex and focus entirely on your manly arts. Rather, competently and rapidly satiate your desire for female companionship; then, having solved the immediate problem of your thirst, you can turn your attention to weightier topics. 

[^1]: South Africa seems to be an exception to the rule&#8212;an effect perhaps explicable by its position at the Commonwealth&#8217;s periphery. At any rate its girls are of a higher caliber on average than what you find on true British or American soil.]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Throw Away Your Television]]></title>
    <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/21/throw-away-your-television/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-21T14:57:54-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/21/throw-away-your-television</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[Who are we to argue with Anthony Kiedis, former mostly-nude drug addled madman extraordinaire, Red Hot Chili Peppers jefe, and sometime Freddy Mercury lookalike? 

<!--more-->

The Chilis&#8217; classic early aught&#8217;s [pop-rock jam](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xLkD7V07f_E) exhorts listeners to &#8220;throw away your television&#8221; with an argument that boils down to &#8220;reruns are boring.&#8221; This is true but misleading, because there are far better reasons to free yourself from the telly&#8217;s suffocating embrace. 

<span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/keidis.jpeg' width='' height='' title='Fig. 1: Mr. Kiedis is recognized as the undisputed world cruiserweight champion of Freddie Mercury impersonators. [^2]'><span class='caption-text'>Fig. 1: Mr. Kiedis is recognized as the undisputed world cruiserweight champion of Freddie Mercury impersonators. [^2]</span></span> 

## I. Construction of Unhealthy Norms

Television is an instrument of state and corporate-industrial-complex propaganda, which therefore promulgates a worldview conducive to the best interests of your society&#8217;s powerful institutions and groups. In many cases, this worldview will explicitly contradict your best interests as a man. If you expose yourself to the persistent socialization shown on sitcoms, the news, popular dramas, etc, your mentality will begin to bend towards the television&#8217;s unstated premise in a subtle and insidious fashion. There are very few truly iconoclastic role models and lifestyles shown on television today, and a near-total absence of ideas about how to live one&#8217;s life devoted to something other than consuming the maximum possible quantities of industrial products. [^1] 

In other words, the Sultan will never suggest that you develop the skills to disrupt his economic system and thereby become independently wealthy, remove yourself from his low-paid labour force, and use your newfound free time to seduce his harem.

## II. Observe Your Elders
Likely very few of the men you respect spend much time watching TV. If they do, it&#8217;s probably live sports or a single show on DVD/Netflix. For example, Bro Kaizen&#8217;s grandfather spends the overwhelming majority of his time reading, writing his memoirs, working in public service, and tooling around in his garden. He watches a single 30-minute programme, once per week&#8212;and this is a man with limited mobility and significant health problems, for whom it would surely be physically very comfortable to descend into a couch-potato existence of grim daytime soap-opera viewing.

Observe several exceptional men&#8212;most of them spend far less time in front of the television than the median male. This is not a cooincidence. One of Bro Kaizen&#8217;s modern role models, Arnold Schwarzenegger[^3], has the following to say about learning from your elders.

<blockquote><p>&#8220;My father was a country police officer. All he knew was discipline, performance, and work&#8212;not wasting your time. He came from an era where everything was scarce, so everything had to be useful&#8230; But it was from him that I got my work ethic.&#8221;</p></blockquote>

He also touches on time wasting, as per section III below. The quote is borrowed from an interview in [Esquire](http://www.esquire.com/features/what-ive-learned/meaning-of-life-2013/arnold-schwarzenegger-quotes-0113), which contains a few of Arnold&#8217;s other _bon mots._ You&#8217;ll notice that at no point does he advocate sitting around lazily in front of the TV.


<span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/arnold.jpg' width='' height='' title='Fig. 2: You should lift more. [^4]'><span class='caption-text'>Fig. 2: You should lift more. [^4]</span></span> 

## III. Money, Time, and Indolence
Television is expensive. The hardware costs might run to the high hundreds or low thousands of Euros for a big flat-panel display, and cable television costs in some countries as much as hundreds of Euros per month for a upper-middle tier package. You have better things to do with this money&#8212;such as investing it in appreciating assets that will contribute to your eventual financial independence. 

Notably, the costs mentioned above do not account for the time spent on a TV habit. Overwhelmingly large piles of money have been spent to sculpt most programmes into expertly crafted attention magnets. It becomes progressively more difficult to extricate yourself from a series&#8217; plotline and psychological effects once you&#8217;ve let it into your life. It will suck your hours away and you will barely notice they&#8217;re gone. 

Lastly, consider the most pernicious effect of the television-watching lifestyle: chronic indolence. Television watching is designed to beget more television watching, and a weekend spent pissing away time on the sofa will [sap your gumption](http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/17/husband-your-gumption/) more than any other experience. This effect is particularly dangerous because gumption is a man&#8217;s most precious resource.

## IV. Exceptions and Counterpoint

We can also play the hypotheticals game&#8212;if Odysseus were alive today, would you find him parked in front of Modern Family? What about Michel de Montaigne? Winston Churchill? Obviously not.

<span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/odysseus.jpg' width='' height='' title='Fig. 3: Artist's rendition of Odysseus demonstrating proper operating procedure when men attempt to have sex with your wife. [^5]'><span class='caption-text'>Fig. 3: Artist&#8217;s rendition of Odysseus demonstrating proper operating procedure when men attempt to have sex with your wife. [^5]</span></span> 

Naturally there are counterexamples, and it isn&#8217;t hard to imagine the immortal bard savoring a laugh at Basil Fawlty&#8217;s expense or the often bawdy Chaucer relishing the unsubtle innuendos of Jersey Shore. But it is a stretch to propose that those men would make TV their primary pastime.

And of course if TV is a bonding experience with your buddies, it becomes something of a different animal. Male friendships are extremely important, and you must work to nurture them. But if all your friends do is lounge around and watch TV, you might need to re-evaluate the company you keep. 

	
[^1]: Parts of the religious media promulgate a broadly nonmaterialist ideology, but by the anthropic principle, any religious organization wealthy and powerful enough to control significant mindshare on broadcast television or the internet will replace commercial TV&#8217;s mantra of &#8220;Buy consumer goods!&#8221; with one similar in all but name, which might be summarized as &#8220;Pay your tithes and become tightly integrated into our religious organization&#8217;s social structure!&#8221;

[^2]: Image courtesy of the fine folks at [Stadium-Arcadium.com](http://stadium-arcadium.com/04-02-2012/look-around-interactive-music-video-behind-the-scenes-part-three/red-hot-chili-peppers-news/article16224/attachment/anthony-kiedis-look-around-interactive-music-video-red-hot-chili-peppers-im-with-you-rhcp-0202), a startlingly exhaustive RHCP fan site. 

[^3]: All the usual caveats apply about Arnold&#8217;s abysmal acting abilities and thick accent. But he stands in the first tier of men who have done difficult things well and bettered themselves significantly in the process.
 
[^4]: Image courtesy of [Jack O&#8217;Quinn](https://www.flickr.com/photos/46502813@N03/5343432134/)

[^5]: Image courtesy of [Wikipedia](http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Odysseus).]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Instruction in Natural Language]]></title>
    <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/18/instruction-in-natural-language/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-18T14:31:02-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/18/instruction-in-natural-language</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[In many college classes and in the knowledge-work industry, you will be required to learn new material from a book. Very likely you will be assigned some reading on the topic, and this reading will probably be from an eminent and respectable tome. When people see you carrying around that tome, or reading it on the tube, they will be quite impressed by your powerful brain. But there's one large drawback.

<!--more-->

## I. Textual Density and Inacessibility

<span class='pullquote-right' data-pullquote='the vital concept in chapter 8 was defined exactly once, four hundred pages ago, in chapter 1.'>
That tome will be utterly unhelpful, written in a language of dense jargon, and of the expectation that you will read the accursed thing from cover to cover in its entirety and with a perfect memory, because the vital concept in chapter 8 was defined exactly once, four hundred pages ago, in chapter 1. Furthermore the location of that definition is not mentioned in chapter 8. Such books are peerless when you _already understand_ the topic and aim to deepen your comprehension. But they are the curse of unproductive death for the novice. The paradigmatic example of this is Gleason and Gordon&#8217;s [_Applied Calculus_](http://www.amazon.com/Applied-Calculus-Deborah-Hughes-Hallett/dp/0470170522), which is often assigned to undergraduates in a calculus course for students who are not mathematics majors. These students would do _overwhelmingly_ better to ignore the (needlessly and insultingly expensive) Gleason and Gordon and instead pick up a text written in natural language for a non-specialist audience. In this case, the best answer is something like [_The Complete Idiot&#8217;s Guide to Calculus_](http://www.amazon.com/Complete-Idiots-Guide-Calculus-Edition/dp/1592574718/ref=dp_ob_title_bk). 
</span>

## II. The General Social Other and Unprestigious Texts
Nobody will be impressed in the slightest when they see you carrying that around. In fact, you&#8217;ll likely be mocked. For this reason, your manager will never hand you a _For Dummies_ or similar title after asking you to figure out a new topic&#8212;it would imply that his company is filled with wankers. Not one professor in all of academia has ever assigned a _Complete Idiot&#8217;s Guide._ But these books are often the most valuable introductory material available anywhere. They assume no prior domain knowledge, tend to treat each chapter as a discrete unit that could be learned alone, are written with many concrete examples, and often include bits of levity to ease the burden of the material&#8217;s density.

Most students feel guilty for ignoring the assigned course text. I hereby give you permission to ignore bad academic material and to make your own decisions about how to optimize learning outcomes. Next time you&#8217;re assigned some dense reading, check to see if you can find a more accessible treatment at one of the following locations or elsewhere:

* [For Dummies](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/For_Dummies), written in a cutesy tone but often quite valuable
* [Complete Idiot&#8217;s guide](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Complete_Idiot%27s_Guides), similarly cutesy, often with groan-inducing humor
* [Better Explained](http://betterexplained.com), which is pure gold
* [The Very Short Introduction Series]( https://global.oup.com/academic/content/series/v/very-short-introductions-vsi/?cc=us&lang=en&), written in a more academic style but generally quite accessible
* [George M. Dallas]( https://georgemdallas.wordpress.com/2014/05/14/wavelets-4-dummies-signal-processing-fourier-transforms-and-heisenberg/), who covers only a handful of technical topics, but does so masterfully.

## III. Oh Ye Theoreticians
Caveat: This advice is for the mere mortals who are getting by on elbow grease and long hours. Obviously this does not apply if you&#8217;re a top-5% theoretical thinker. You know who you are. Why are you reading this blog? Go forth and conquer that [special topics seminar in differential geometry](http://maths.anu.edu.au/math3349-special-topics-mathematics-differential-geometry). ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Maximizing Productivity]]></title>
    <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/11/maximizing-productivity/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-11T18:27:21-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/11/maximizing-productivity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[Napoleon said something like (paraphrasing aggressively here), "The results of every battle are determined ahead of time by the geography, weather, and factors pertaining to the supply of war _materiel_." 

This notion of meta-factors' outsized importance also applies to studying, especially in college.

<!--more-->

When you are studying hard, your brain will become attuned to small details. It is best to point this detail-oriented focus at the text you&#8217;re trying to learn, such as Andrew Ng&#8217;s [Machine Learning course](http://www.holehouse.org/mlclass/) or one of my personal favorite MOOC&#8217;s, _The Theory and Practice of Dodge Diesel Truck Repair for Strongly Heteronormative Men._

In most candidate study locations, there will be a million small distractions that, when compounded, will significantly diminish your focus. Do not waste your mental _oomph_ on small blinking lights on the back of an HP Elitebook&#8217;s NIC, loud IT managers, people walking in your field of view, etc. It is _so important_ to find somewhere with very few audiovisual distractions, where you know you can be productive. 

Instead of taking the first seat in the library that comes into view, you ought to find the single canonically best place to study, and then study there every single time.
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
