<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Foundations | Bro Kaizen]]></title>
  <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/categories/foundations/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-16T01:05:57-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://bro-kaizen.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[bro_kaizen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Throw Away Your Television]]></title>
    <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/21/throw-away-your-television/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-21T14:57:54-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/21/throw-away-your-television</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[Who are we to argue with Anthony Kiedis, former mostly-nude drug addled madman extraordinaire, Red Hot Chili Peppers jefe, and sometime Freddy Mercury lookalike? 

<!--more-->

The Chilis&#8217; classic early aught&#8217;s [pop-rock jam](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xLkD7V07f_E) exhorts listeners to &#8220;throw away your television&#8221; with an argument that boils down to &#8220;reruns are boring.&#8221; This is true but misleading, because there are far better reasons to free yourself from the telly&#8217;s suffocating embrace. 

<span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/keidis.jpeg' width='' height='' title='Fig. 1: Mr. Kiedis is recognized as the undisputed world cruiserweight champion of Freddie Mercury impersonators. [^2]'><span class='caption-text'>Fig. 1: Mr. Kiedis is recognized as the undisputed world cruiserweight champion of Freddie Mercury impersonators. [^2]</span></span> 

## I. Construction of Unhealthy Norms

Television is an instrument of state and corporate-industrial-complex propaganda, which therefore promulgates a worldview conducive to the best interests of your society&#8217;s powerful institutions and groups. In many cases, this worldview will explicitly contradict your best interests as a man. If you expose yourself to the persistent socialization shown on sitcoms, the news, popular dramas, etc, your mentality will begin to bend towards the television&#8217;s unstated premise in a subtle and insidious fashion. There are very few truly iconoclastic role models and lifestyles shown on television today, and a near-total absence of ideas about how to live one&#8217;s life devoted to something other than consuming the maximum possible quantities of industrial products. [^1] 

In other words, the Sultan will never suggest that you develop the skills to disrupt his economic system and thereby become independently wealthy, remove yourself from his low-paid labour force, and use your newfound free time to seduce his harem.

## II. Observe Your Elders
Likely very few of the men you respect spend much time watching TV. If they do, it&#8217;s probably live sports or a single show on DVD/Netflix. For example, Bro Kaizen&#8217;s grandfather spends the overwhelming majority of his time reading, writing his memoirs, working in public service, and tooling around in his garden. He watches a single 30-minute programme, once per week&#8212;and this is a man with limited mobility and significant health problems, for whom it would surely be physically very comfortable to descend into a couch-potato existence of grim daytime soap-opera viewing.

Observe several exceptional men&#8212;most of them spend far less time in front of the television than the median male. This is not a cooincidence. One of Bro Kaizen&#8217;s modern role models, Arnold Schwarzenegger[^3], has the following to say about learning from your elders.

<blockquote><p>&#8220;My father was a country police officer. All he knew was discipline, performance, and work&#8212;not wasting your time. He came from an era where everything was scarce, so everything had to be useful&#8230; But it was from him that I got my work ethic.&#8221;</p></blockquote>

He also touches on time wasting, as per section III below. The quote is borrowed from an interview in [Esquire](http://www.esquire.com/features/what-ive-learned/meaning-of-life-2013/arnold-schwarzenegger-quotes-0113), which contains a few of Arnold&#8217;s other _bon mots._ You&#8217;ll notice that at no point does he advocate sitting around lazily in front of the TV.


<span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/arnold.jpg' width='' height='' title='Fig. 2: You should lift more. [^4]'><span class='caption-text'>Fig. 2: You should lift more. [^4]</span></span> 

## III. Money, Time, and Indolence
Television is expensive. The hardware costs might run to the high hundreds or low thousands of Euros for a big flat-panel display, and cable television costs in some countries as much as hundreds of Euros per month for a upper-middle tier package. You have better things to do with this money&#8212;such as investing it in appreciating assets that will contribute to your eventual financial independence. 

Notably, the costs mentioned above do not account for the time spent on a TV habit. Overwhelmingly large piles of money have been spent to sculpt most programmes into expertly crafted attention magnets. It becomes progressively more difficult to extricate yourself from a series&#8217; plotline and psychological effects once you&#8217;ve let it into your life. It will suck your hours away and you will barely notice they&#8217;re gone. 

Lastly, consider the most pernicious effect of the television-watching lifestyle: chronic indolence. Television watching is designed to beget more television watching, and a weekend spent pissing away time on the sofa will [sap your gumption](http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/17/husband-your-gumption/) more than any other experience. This effect is particularly dangerous because gumption is a man&#8217;s most precious resource.

## IV. Exceptions and Counterpoint

We can also play the hypotheticals game&#8212;if Odysseus were alive today, would you find him parked in front of Modern Family? What about Michel de Montaigne? Winston Churchill? Obviously not.

<span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/odysseus.jpg' width='' height='' title='Fig. 3: Artist's rendition of Odysseus demonstrating proper operating procedure when men attempt to have sex with your wife. [^5]'><span class='caption-text'>Fig. 3: Artist&#8217;s rendition of Odysseus demonstrating proper operating procedure when men attempt to have sex with your wife. [^5]</span></span> 

Naturally there are counterexamples, and it isn&#8217;t hard to imagine the immortal bard savoring a laugh at Basil Fawlty&#8217;s expense or the often bawdy Chaucer relishing the unsubtle innuendos of Jersey Shore. But it is a stretch to propose that those men would make TV their primary pastime.

And of course if TV is a bonding experience with your buddies, it becomes something of a different animal. Male friendships are extremely important, and you must work to nurture them. But if all your friends do is lounge around and watch TV, you might need to re-evaluate the company you keep. 

	
[^1]: Parts of the religious media promulgate a broadly nonmaterialist ideology, but by the anthropic principle, any religious organization wealthy and powerful enough to control significant mindshare on broadcast television or the internet will replace commercial TV&#8217;s mantra of &#8220;Buy consumer goods!&#8221; with one similar in all but name, which might be summarized as &#8220;Pay your tithes and become tightly integrated into our religious organization&#8217;s social structure!&#8221;

[^2]: Image courtesy of the fine folks at [Stadium-Arcadium.com](http://stadium-arcadium.com/04-02-2012/look-around-interactive-music-video-behind-the-scenes-part-three/red-hot-chili-peppers-news/article16224/attachment/anthony-kiedis-look-around-interactive-music-video-red-hot-chili-peppers-im-with-you-rhcp-0202), a startlingly exhaustive RHCP fan site. 

[^3]: All the usual caveats apply about Arnold&#8217;s abysmal acting abilities and thick accent. But he stands in the first tier of men who have done difficult things well and bettered themselves significantly in the process.
 
[^4]: Image courtesy of [Jack O&#8217;Quinn](https://www.flickr.com/photos/46502813@N03/5343432134/)

[^5]: Image courtesy of [Wikipedia](http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Odysseus).]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Expert Instruction]]></title>
    <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/20/expert-instruction/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-20T00:46:55-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/20/expert-instruction</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[Deliberate practice is hard. Sometimes, you can cheat that difficulty by finding a reliable expert who has written a how-to guide, and following the recipe exactly. This is an extension of the notion that you should [find user-friendly instruction](http://localhost:4000/blog/2014/11/18/instruction-in-natural-language/) if possible, and was stolen blatantly from Lyle McDonald at Body Recomposition. 

In his [entertaining rant](http://www.bodyrecomposition.com/just-do-the-program/), Lyle says, 

<!--more-->

<blockquote><p>&#8230;for the first year of training with him, I did everything he said exactly as he told me to do it.  He was the expert and regardless of what I thought I knew, I had hired him for a reason. In fact, I didn’t even know enough about ice speed skating at that point to have an opinion.  As they put it in martial arts training, I shut the hell up and swept dojo.</p></blockquote>

Often, a reliable expert&#8217;s walkthrough will essentially cause you to emulate a regimen of directed practice, but all the thinking has been done for you. So you just have to commit to walking over to your DVD player every morning and pushing play or opening the book and doing as you&#8217;re told. This is really valuable, both in the immediate sense of making gains in whatever topic you&#8217;re learning, but also in a subtler meta-sense; this &#8220;guided directed practice&#8221; builds intuition about learning new skills in the extra-curricular environment. After you do a few practice runs of learning new skills by having your hand held by the experts, you&#8217;ll get a sense of how credible instruction and steady skill building feels.

<span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/skating.jpg' width='' height='' title='Fig. 1: Not Lyle himself, but you better believe this girl can throw down some squats. [^1]'><span class='caption-text'>Fig. 1: Not Lyle himself, but you better believe this girl can throw down some squats. [^1]</span></span> 

### Examples of reliable expert walkthroughs for fitness:

* Mark Rippetoe&#8217;s [Starting Strength](http://www.seriouspowerlifting.com/3409/articles/starting-strength) book and videos (for making you strong)
* The [P90X](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/P90X) program of fitness DVD&#8217;s and diet (for giving you beach muscles)
* Lynn McDonald&#8217;s [Body Recomposition](http://www.bodyrecomposition.com) website (for making you skinny ripped)
* [Juggling for the Complete Klutz]( http://www.amazon.com/Juggling-Complete-Klutz-Anniversary-Edition/dp/1591744482)

Does juggling count as fitness? Definitely not. But it&#8217;s a great low-risk skill for kids, and this is the book that got me started on the growth mentality and Kaizen, so it has a special place in my heart. And it&#8217;s really, really good at teaching you how to juggle. Which is incidentally a pretty good starter skill for building momentum on the whole business of learning new things, even if you&#8217;re a grown man. 

<span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/graham.jpg' width='' height='' title='Fig. 2: Ron Graham can furnish expert instruction in topics far more profound than circus tricks.[^2]'><span class='caption-text'>Fig. 2: Ron Graham can furnish expert instruction in topics far more profound than circus tricks.[^2]</span></span> 

Ultimately, borrowing experts&#8217; ideas is a time efficient hack for discovering domain-specific best practices. When beginning a new discipline, such as fitness or juggling or whatever else, it&#8217;s almost always worth starting under the auspices of some formalized progam if possible.

[^1]: Image courtesy of [Wikipedia](http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephanie_Beckert)

[^2]: Image courtesy of [Wikipedia](http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ronald_Graham)]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Stackable Permanent Life Improvements]]></title>
    <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/19/stackable-permanent-life-improvements/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-19T16:11:46-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/19/stackable-permanent-life-improvements</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[Amy Chua's [Tiger Mother](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_Hymn_of_the_Tiger_Mother) book claims _delayed gratification_ as one of the three invariant characteristics of high-performing immigrant populations. She's on to something, but we can generalize her idea and do one better.

<!--more-->

<span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/chua.jpg' width='300' height='150' title='Fig. 1: The Tiger Mother  in her native habitat. [^1]'><span class='caption-text'>Fig. 1: The Tiger Mother  in her native habitat. [^1]</span></span> 

Given finite time, money, concentration, and gumption, every man must make decisions about resource expenditure. In general, it is best to aim to expend your resources solely upon &#8220;Stackable Permanent Life Improvements,&#8221; instead of mere delayed gratification.

Stackable Permanent Life Improvements are new additions to your life that add value, don&#8217;t expire, and can be compounded. Another way of saying this&#8212;stolen from Bro Kaizen&#8217;s crusty and implausibly rich old uncle&#8212;is, &#8220;Only buy things that appreciate.&#8221; What he means is that you ought to only exchange your resources for things that have lasting value and are composable (in the computer science sense of composability). 

###Examples of Stackable Permament Life Improvements:

- Learning a new language (Russian, Pashto, pig latin)
- Buying assets that will appreciate or throw off positive cash flows indefinitely (bonds, equities, real estate, whatever).
- Gaining experience talking to pretty girls, such that you give off a jaded and experienced vibe and are not intimidated by the next Finnish model you meet.[^2]
- Learning a new skill, such as how to squat with good form. This will allow you to improve your physical fitness indefinitely in the future.
- Learning new theory that deepens your understanding of the world. Example: You read [Haberman](http://www.amazon.com/Applied-Partial-Differential-Equations-Boundary/dp/0130652431)&#8217;s book on partial differential equations. You have gained a more fundamental understanding of the world around you, by understanding more about heat transfer and wave phenomena (among other topics). 


But beware! Do not be bamboozled by things that make you feel good now, and perhaps seem superficially similar to SPLI&#8217;s, but are not in fact the genuine article. 

###Examples of Stackable but Non-permanent life improvements:

- You buy a delicious cake from the bakery and eat it. It is tasty at the time but if you want to get that taste again, you&#8217;ll have to buy another one.
- You spend time playing Halo, which is very enjoyable but doesn&#8217;t pay dividends beyond slightly improved hand-eye coordination.
- Your rugby coach praises your performance as a rucker. This praise makes you feel good, but afterwards you begin to rest on your laurels.

<span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/cake.jpg' width='' height='' title='Fig. 2: Straight up delicious. [^3]'><span class='caption-text'>Fig. 2: Straight up delicious. [^3]</span></span> 

Many of these will stack easily&#8212;e.g. you could easily eat cake while playing Halo. But they don&#8217;t last. The real-deal stackable permanent life improvements tend to fall into a few buckets: 

###Common sorts of SPLI&#8217;s:

- Learning new stuff, such as practical skills or theories
- Financial improvements (new investments or appreciating/cash flow positive property)
- Gaining credentials, such as degrees or fellowships, that can be used to convince other people and The Establishment of your value
- New relationships with people

Of course, there are probably plenty of other broad buckets. But keep an eye out for the ones above, as they&#8217;re some of the most common.

And if pissing away your Sunday playing Halo is a male bonding activity that you do with your bros, that solidifies strong friendships for life, then by all means count it as a SPLI. But in that case, expenditure of the Sunday should by rights be filed under &#8220;Male Bonding,&#8221; not &#8220;Halo.&#8221;

[^1]: Image courtesy of [Wikipedia](http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Amy_Chua_2012_Shankbone.JPG)

[^2]: Has Bro Kaizen ever met a Finnish model? Or for that matter, any Finnish person at all? Certainly not. But a guy can dream, right?

[^3]: Image courtesy of [Wikipedia](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cake)]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Instruction in Natural Language]]></title>
    <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/18/instruction-in-natural-language/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-18T14:31:02-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/18/instruction-in-natural-language</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[In many college classes and in the knowledge-work industry, you will be required to learn new material from a book. Very likely you will be assigned some reading on the topic, and this reading will probably be from an eminent and respectable tome. When people see you carrying around that tome, or reading it on the tube, they will be quite impressed by your powerful brain. But there's one large drawback.

<!--more-->

## I. Textual Density and Inacessibility

<span class='pullquote-right' data-pullquote='the vital concept in chapter 8 was defined exactly once, four hundred pages ago, in chapter 1.'>
That tome will be utterly unhelpful, written in a language of dense jargon, and of the expectation that you will read the accursed thing from cover to cover in its entirety and with a perfect memory, because the vital concept in chapter 8 was defined exactly once, four hundred pages ago, in chapter 1. Furthermore the location of that definition is not mentioned in chapter 8. Such books are peerless when you _already understand_ the topic and aim to deepen your comprehension. But they are the curse of unproductive death for the novice. The paradigmatic example of this is Gleason and Gordon&#8217;s [_Applied Calculus_](http://www.amazon.com/Applied-Calculus-Deborah-Hughes-Hallett/dp/0470170522), which is often assigned to undergraduates in a calculus course for students who are not mathematics majors. These students would do _overwhelmingly_ better to ignore the (needlessly and insultingly expensive) Gleason and Gordon and instead pick up a text written in natural language for a non-specialist audience. In this case, the best answer is something like [_The Complete Idiot&#8217;s Guide to Calculus_](http://www.amazon.com/Complete-Idiots-Guide-Calculus-Edition/dp/1592574718/ref=dp_ob_title_bk). 
</span>

## II. The General Social Other and Unprestigious Texts
Nobody will be impressed in the slightest when they see you carrying that around. In fact, you&#8217;ll likely be mocked. For this reason, your manager will never hand you a _For Dummies_ or similar title after asking you to figure out a new topic&#8212;it would imply that his company is filled with wankers. Not one professor in all of academia has ever assigned a _Complete Idiot&#8217;s Guide._ But these books are often the most valuable introductory material available anywhere. They assume no prior domain knowledge, tend to treat each chapter as a discrete unit that could be learned alone, are written with many concrete examples, and often include bits of levity to ease the burden of the material&#8217;s density.

Most students feel guilty for ignoring the assigned course text. I hereby give you permission to ignore bad academic material and to make your own decisions about how to optimize learning outcomes. Next time you&#8217;re assigned some dense reading, check to see if you can find a more accessible treatment at one of the following locations or elsewhere:

* [For Dummies](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/For_Dummies), written in a cutesy tone but often quite valuable
* [Complete Idiot&#8217;s guide](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Complete_Idiot%27s_Guides), similarly cutesy, often with groan-inducing humor
* [Better Explained](http://betterexplained.com), which is pure gold
* [The Very Short Introduction Series]( https://global.oup.com/academic/content/series/v/very-short-introductions-vsi/?cc=us&lang=en&), written in a more academic style but generally quite accessible
* [George M. Dallas]( https://georgemdallas.wordpress.com/2014/05/14/wavelets-4-dummies-signal-processing-fourier-transforms-and-heisenberg/), who covers only a handful of technical topics, but does so masterfully.

## III. Oh Ye Theoreticians
Caveat: This advice is for the mere mortals who are getting by on elbow grease and long hours. Obviously this does not apply if you&#8217;re a top-5% theoretical thinker. You know who you are. Why are you reading this blog? Go forth and conquer that [special topics seminar in differential geometry](http://maths.anu.edu.au/math3349-special-topics-mathematics-differential-geometry). ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On Gumption and Character]]></title>
    <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/16/on-gumption-and-character/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-16T02:01:53-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/16/on-gumption-and-character</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[Gumption is the gasoline of man's life. It is the get-up-and-go, the stick-to-it-iveness, and the knocked-down-twice, stand-up-thrice fire inside you. If you run out of it, things will head south very quickly. You must cultivate this gumption, nurture it, and encourage it to grow. Every man possesses by nature a certain rate of gumption replenishment, which rate may be modified by nurture. As you nurture your rate of gumption replenishment, you will also tend to develop in parallel the ability to store more of it. I know of at least two ways to develop gumption:

<!--more-->


* Acclimatizing oneself to doing things that are hard (I am blatantly stealing this from [Mark Rippetoe](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_Rippetoe)&#8217;s book Starting Strength, in the chapter on deadlifts)
* Experiencing deprivation or scarcity

## I. Population Distribution of Gumption
There exists a gumption spectrum, upon which we can plot the positions of any given person. For rhetorical purposes, let&#8217;s bookend the spectrum with Navy SEALS (the ultra-elite amphibious stormtroopers of the American war machine) on one end, and the decadent, privileged children of the American upper-middle class on the other. (Oddly enough, the real aristocrats have often gone to great lengths to develop their children&#8217;s character, even in the most decadent of societies. For this reason there exist scathingly difficult elite boarding schools, summers spent as ranch hands, and dangerous or physics-based hobbies such as Polo and sailboat racing. Witness [Teddy Roosevelt](http://www.thecrimson.com/article/1957/12/12/theodore-roosevelt-at-harvard-pthe-crimson/), a blue blood through and through, and of a character to go toe-to-toe with the best of them. So the social class with the weakest character ends up being the upper-middle.)

Privileged Western white girls/JAP girls are usually typical examples of the no-gumption population, because they have been coddled their whole lives. Their parents have paid for their expensive apartments, unlimited mobile phone plans, vehicles/fuel/insurance, unbelievable quantities of international travel, etc. And if they are _hot_ privileged girls, clueless men have been buying them things/fawning over them/treating them like princesses for many years in a (guaranteed fruitless) attempt to get in their pants. They have experienced neither deprivation nor training in doing hard things, and these missing experiences have eroded/inhibited their character to an alarming degree. (To avoid accusations of hasty generalization, it is worth noting that this is certainly not an accurate description of _all_ privileged Western girls, merely some/many).

## II. Metrology

Obviously there is no such thing as a gumption meter, and it is difficult to measure directly. However, acceptable proxy metrics are available. Resistance to [decision fatigue](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Decision_fatigue) is a reliable predictor of gumption. If you hang out with some rich girls from your school for an afternoon, you&#8217;ll quickly realize that some of them can make a median of 2 decisions before becoming pissy and whiny&#8212;even trivial choices about which shoes to wear or restaurant/bar to visit wear them out. Conversely, imagine an afternoon spent with a Navy SEAL. He has spent his adult life making literal life-or-death decisions about which grade of armor piercing munitions to load in his helicopter, what rate to expel air from his lungs while submerged in icy saltwater, etc. You could require him to choose restaurants and find his way around a strange city for literally weeks on end (tasks which would incite many tantrums from someone on the other end of the spectrum), and he would not show the slightest sign of feeling pressured. 

## III. On Weak Men

Naturally, women are not to be found alone on the no-gumption end of the spectrum&#8212;there are plenty of weak, insipid men cowering there too, particularly in locales that have insulated the citizenry from deprivation, real work, and difficult tasks. And of course there are women on the SEAL end of the spectrum, as well. The Israelis have done a very impressive job of developing a gender-integrated military, complete with female commandos who demonstrate gumption with the best of them (undoubtedly far more gumption than I will ever possess). 

So the point is that gumption is another skill-based-upon-an-aptitude. Each of us is born with a natural level of gumption, but that level can be modified by intentional or unintentional nurture. Your job, as a man, even one in a &#8220;soft&#8221; society, is to take concious steps to regenerate and store more gumption.
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
